A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 9, Accession 9 FA1191
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Exchanges - General, 1971-2012; 2; 5.76 Cubic Feet
  - Chinese Delegations to Other Countries - Clippings File, circa 1971 - 1977 (Box 63)
    Card file of clippings concerning Chinese delegations to other countries, taken mainly from Ta Kung Pao newspaper.
  - Separated Oversized Material (Box 65)
- Exchanges to China, 1972-1986, 2002; 3; 4.27 Cubic Feet 11 containers
  Series 3, Exchanges to China, contains records of the trips the National Committee organized for its Members from 1981-1984, along with trip reports and reference files on individual visits or delegations to China arranged under the auspices of other organizations. Series 3 also includes a few reference Lists of Trips and Exchanges (from the mid-1960s to the late-1970s), arranged by date and by subject category, and including a listing of NCUSCR-facilitated visits.
  Please note that there is some overlap between Travelers and Other Organizations files in Series 3 and the Trip Reports and Other Visits files that are found in Series 2; material on visits to China can be found in both series.
  - Tours to China (General), 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    Brochure on China Passage bicycle tours, 1981; list of agencies sponsoring tours to China, 1982.
  - Members Trips (1981 - General) (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 1) - Applications and Bios, 1981 April 29 - May 17 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 1) - Correspondence with Chinese, 1981 April 29 - May 17 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 1) - Correspondence with Members, 1981 April 29 - May 17 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 1) - Tour Escort Robert Nichols, 1981 April 29 - May 17 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    Includes itinerary and escort's trip report.
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 1) - Financial and Travel Arrangements, 1981 April 29 - May 17 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Members Delegation (1981, No. 2), 1981 September 5-24 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Members Trips (1982 - General) (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Includes Financial and Travel Record for 1982 trips, plus Luxingshe accounting statements, 1979-1981.
  - Members Delegation (1982, No. 1) - Applications, Bios, Correspondence, and Planning, 1982 April 7-28 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Members Delegation (1982, No. 1) - Tour Escort John Thomson, 1982 April 7-28 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    Includes trip report.
  - Members Delegation (1982, No. 4) - General Information and Planning, 1982 October 24 - November 13 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Members Delegation (1982, No. 4) - Applications and Visa Forms, 1982 October 24 - November 13 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Members Delegation (1982, No. 4) - Correspondence with Members, 1982 October 24 - November 13 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Members Delegation (1982, No. 4) - Tour Escort Robert Nichols, 1982 October 24 - November 13 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Special Tour for Richard Paisner and Christine Weiner, 1982 September 4-20 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Members Trips - Inquiries for 1983, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Members Trips (1983 - General) (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 1) - General Information and Planning, 1983 May 20 - June 9 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 1) - Applications, Visa Forms, and Correspondence with Members, 1983 May 20 - June 9 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 1) - Tour Escort Robert Nichols, 1983 May 20 - June 9 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    Audio recording of trip report separated from file. No transcript in file.
    - Report by Robert Nichols on Members Delegation (1983, No. 1), 1983 May 20 - June 9; Compact cassette tape, 90 minutes. (Box 7, Folder 77)
      Two sides, Part 1 and Part 2. No transcript in file.
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 2) (Tibet Trip), 1983 circa September 3-25 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 3) - General Information, Applications, Visa Forms, Correspondence with the Chinese, 1983 September 18 - October 8 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 3) - Correspondence with Members, 1983 September 18 - October 8 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 3) - Tour Escort Gerald Stryker, 1983 September 18 - October 8 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Members Delegation (1983, No. 4) (Cancelled), 1983 (September 21 - October 11) (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Donn Tatum Trip to China, 1983 April 18 - May 1 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Carl and Desanka Hess Trip to China, 1983 September 24 - October 15 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Clifton and Margaret Daniel Trip to China, 1983 October (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Members Delegation (1984, No. 1) - General, 1984 April 28 - May 15 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    Includes applications, correspondence with members, and correspondence with Chinese.
  - Members Delegation (1984, No. 1) -Tour Escort Thomas Robinson, 1984 April 28 - May 15 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    Correspondence file. There is no trip report in file.
  - Members Delegation (1984, No. 2), 1984 May 30 - June 21 (Box 8, Folder 88)
    Includes trip report by tour escort William Ayers.
  - Members Delegation (1984, No. 3) (Cancelled), 1984 September 3-23 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    Applications.
  - Members Delegation (1984, No. 4) - General, 1984 October 23 - November 14 (Box 8, Folder 90)
    General information and planning, applications, correspondence with members, and communications with the Chinese.
  - Members Delegation (1984, No. 4) - Tour Escort Peter Van Ness, 1984 October 23 - November 14 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - National Academy of Arbitrators Trip (Cancelled), 1985 June (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Health Insurance Plan (HIP) Physicians' Trip (Cancelled), 1985 October 22 - November 6 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China (General), 1972-1976 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China (General), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China (General), 1978 (Box 9, Folder 95.1 - 95.2)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China (General), 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 95.3)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China - Medical, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 95.4)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China - Universities, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 95.5)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China - Student Groups, 1972-1979 (Box 9, Folder 95.6 - 95.7)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China - Women's Groups, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 95.8)
  - Other Organizations - Travelers to China - United States Table Tennis Association, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 95.9)
    Proposed travel in China enroute to world championships in Pyongyang, April-May 1979.
  - Other Organizations - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), First Delegation, 1972 September 29 - October 22 (Box 9, Folder 95. 10)
  - Other Organizations - Chicago Model Cities Program Youth Delegation, 1973 summer (Box 10, Folder 96)
    Delegation of inner-city youth to China. Original folder also labeled "Great Chicago Exposition" (reflecting changes in the planned orientation program).
  - Other Organizations - New York State Education Department Delegations, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    Study tour of China by college and secondary school educators, July 1973. A second delegation trip, planned for spring 1974, was cancelled.
  - Other Organizations -Albert Yee Proposed Educational Exchanges, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 98)
    Yee, a professor of Education, visited China in December 1972 and was attempting to arrange further exchanges.
  - Other Organizations - Philadelphia Council for International Visitors Delegation, 1974 October 7-27 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Other Organizations -Guardian Delegations, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    Exchange trips organized by The Guardian, including a January 1975 trip for Farmers and Farmworkers.
  - Other Organizations - American Association of State Colleges and Universities, 1975 April 1-21 (Box 10, Folder 101)
    See also Individual report on China trip by Emerson Shuck, in Trip Reports - Education, box, folder.
  - Other Organizations - Mayor's Committee on International Visitors (Washington, DC), 1975 April 6-29 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Other Organizations - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), Second Delegation, 1975 May 29 - June 22 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Other Organizations - League of Women Voters of Illinois and American Association of University Women Delegation, 1976 January 7-18 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Other Organizations - Chicago COSERV Delegation, 1976 February (Box 10, Folder 105)
    Council for Community Services to International Visitors (COSERV).
  - Other Organizations - Bucks County (PA) Educators Delegation, 1976 April 16 - May 6 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    Contents date from1 973-1976.
  - Other Organizations - Arizona Education Association Visit, 1976 July (Box 10, Folder 107)
    Includes correspondence from 1972-1976
  - Other Organizations - San Francisco International Hospitality Center Delegation, 1976 September (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Other Organizations - Memphis Council for International Friendship Visit, 1976 October 12-29 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Other Organizations - Arizona International Women's Delegation (Margo Lea-Dudley), 1976 October-November (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Other Organizations - National Delegation of American Women Professional Leaders, 1977 January (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Other Organizations - Decorators Club Delegation, 1977 October (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Other Organizations - Atlanta Council for International Visitors Delegation, 1977 October 14-29 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Other Organizations - American Nurses' Association Study Tour, 1977 November 14 - December 7 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Other Organizations - Connecticut Falcons Women's Softball Team Proposed Visit, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Other Organizations - American Society for Public Administration Delegation, 1978 March 14-28 (Box 11, Folder 116)
    Contents dated 1975-1978.
  - Other Organizations - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), Third Delegation, 1978 September-October (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Municipal Finance in China Workshop Delegation, 2002 November 30 - December 11 (Box 23, Folder 232)
    Study tour cosponsored with the Woodrow Wilson Center. File also includes some information on the Hazardous Waste delegation, June 22 - July 5, 2002.
  - Notes and Bibliography on Travel and Business, 1980-1981 (Box 25, Folder 234)
    Richard J. Smith, Notes on China Travel, December 1980; David L. Denny, "Doing Business with China," 1981.
  - FAO China Resource Guide, 1976 June - July; Physical Condition: Mimeograph publication on acidic paper. (Box 25, Folder 235)
    Working Paper, Preliminary Draft. Prepared by Philip R. Thomforde, Development Division, Food and Agriculture Organization. Includes Partial List of Reports of Recent Visitors to the People's Republic of China, available in the files of the NCUSCR, 1977 February 18. Lists reports and papers by recent visitors to China, 1956 - 1976.
  - Lists of Trip Reports and Exchanges, 1976-1980 (Box 25, Folder 236)
    Lists compiled circa 1976-1978. Trips and reports range in date from 1964 - 1980, but date mainly from 1972 - 1976. File includes chronological lists and lists by subject area. File also includes a list of Facilitated Exchanges to and from China, 1972-1979.
  - Trip Reports - General, 1971-1980 (Box 25, Folder 237-240)
  - Trip Reports - General, 1980-1986; undated (Box 25, Folder 241)
    Includes John Seabury Thomson's reports on Shanghai American School trips to China, 1980-1981; and undated "Notes on Trip to Harbin" ( sponsored by the Hawaii Chinese - American Friendship Society).
  - A Journey to China: First New York Study Group on Modern China, 1973 July (Box 25, Folder 242)
    Background Notes on Interviews and Institutional Visits and Other Data, by Ward Morehouse. Center for International Programs and Comparative Studies, State Education Department, State University of the State of New York, Albany. Volume 1, October 1973.
  - Michael Lindsay, China Revisited, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 243)
    Lord Lindsay of Birker.
  - F. W. Mote, American Linguistics Delegation, 1974 October 16 - November 13 (Box 26, Folder 244)
    China in 1950 and China in 1974: Some Superficial Observations on the Changes of a Quarter-Century.
  - U. S. - China Peoples Friendship Association Mid-West Region Delegation - Travel Notes, 1974 November (Box 26, Folder 245)
  - Fund for Peace Delegation, 1979 February- March (Box 26, Folder 247)
    Trip report by James F. Tierney, April 1979.
  - Foreign Policy Association Directors Delegation Report, 1979 May 29 - June 19 (Box 26, Folder 248)
  - Brown University Chorus Trip, 1979 June-July (Box 26, Folder 249)
  - U. S. - China Peoples Friendship Association Regional Leaders Tour, 1979 September 7 - October 5 (Box 26, Folder 250)
    Transcript of briefing notes. Sent by Betty Goff Cartwright.
  - Report on the Visit to the People's Republic of China and Indonesia by the Delegation from the United States Committee for Unicef, 1980 March 31 - April 25 (Box 26, Folder 251)
  - Michigan State University First Mission to the PRC, 1980 September 10-30 (Box 26, Folder 252)
  - Ronald Reagan Visit to China - Background, 1984 April (Box 53, Folder 523)
  - Separated Oversized Material (Box 65)
- Exchanges from China, 1972-1993; 4; 2.26 Cubic Feet 3 containers
  - Potential Visits to the United States, 1992-1993 (Box 53, Folder 524)
    Correspondence to and from David M. Lampton. Concerns visits from the State Council Research Office and the Commission for the Reform of the Economic Structure, among others.
  - Shenyang Acrobats - Press Clippings, 1972 November - 1973 January (Box 60, Folder 590)
  - Central Television Purchasing Delegation, 1982 September 29 - October 28 (Box 60, Folder 591)
  - Basketball Visit Banner, circa 1978 November; Realia: Textile (Banner). Banner is approximately 26 feet long and 3 feet wide. (Box 66)
    Welcome banner, presumably displayed during visit of Men's and Women's Basketball teams from China, 1978 November 8-19.
    Due to the dimensions of this item, it cannot be viewed in the RAC reading room. Access is restricted at the discretion of RAC.
- Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues, 1965-2009; 5; 1.7 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes and 2 legal boxes
  Series 5, Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues, notably contains files on the National Conference on the United States and China, which was held in Washington, DC, April 28-30, 1965, and which provided some impetus for the creation and organization of the NCUSCR the following year. Records of the National Committee's March 1971 seminar on Taiwan and American Policy make up the other significant component of the Conferences series in RG 9. Other materials include a descriptive list of Conversations from Wingspread recordings, 1972-1979, as well as a few files that complement records in other parts of the NCUSCR collections.
  - National Conference on the United States and China, 1965 April 29-30; Still Images: Black and white photos, contact sheets, and negatives. (Box 1, Folder 1, 2)
    Includes 1 image with President Johnson, and negatives.
  - National Conference on the United States and China (Speeches), 1965 April 28-30 (Box 1, Folder 3, 4)
  - American Interests in China's Ecology, 1992 November 18 (Box 51, Folder 498)
    Meeting at World Resources Institute, Washington, DC.
  - Media Conference - Press Advisory, 1998 June (Box 51, Folder 499)
    Conference on United States Media Coverage of China, May 1998, held in preparation for President Clinton's visit to China.
  - Convocation on the U.S. and China - Press Coverage, 1969 (Box 59, Folder 573)
    National convocation on "The United States and China: The Next Decade," 1969 March 20-21.
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar - Proceedings, 1971 March 5-6 (Box 59, Folder 574-576)
    The Taiwan Factor in America's China Policy. Seminar cosponsored by the National Committee and the League of Women Voters Education Fund, Washington, DC. Luncheon and Dinner meetings, March 5; Morning Session, Summary and Press Conference, March 6.
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar - Program Planning and Development, 1970-1971 (Box 59, Folder 577)
    The Taiwan Factor in America's China Policy.
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar - Alexander Eckstein Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 59, Folder 578)
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar - Participant Correspondence, 1971 March 5-6 (Box 60, Folder 579)
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar - Program and Background Readings, 1971 March 5-6 (Box 60, Folder 580)
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar -Papers and Drafts, 1971 (Box 60, Folder 581-582)
  - Taiwan and American Policy Seminar - Book Publication, 1971 (Box 60, Folder 583)
    Taiwan and American Policy: The Dilemma in U.S. - China Relations,Praeger, 1971. Correspondence file.
  - Wingspread Conference - Exchange Experience with China - The Past, Present and Future, 1977 February 20-21 (Box 60, Folder 584)
    Correspondence, background, and planning. See also FA1186, RG 4, box 60, folder 585, for conference program and materials.
  - Conversations from Wingspread - Recordings on China, 1972-1979 (Box 60, Folder 585)
    Descriptive sheets on 26 recordings of National Committee and other Wingspread programs on China. Descriptions include catalogue number, topic, date, length, participants, and frequently a snynopsis of the discussion. For recordings in the series, see FA1318.
  - U. S. Foreign Policy Colloquium - Planning, 2003 June 5-8 (Box 60, Folder 586)
  - Thirtieth Anniversary of the Normalization of U. S. - China Relations Seminar - Planning, 2009 January (Box 60, Folder 587)
    Email exchange concerning event planning, November 2008.
  - Outside Conferences - United Nations Millennium Development Goals Symposium, 2003 April 29 (Box 60, Folder 588)
    Columbia University. Includes notes.
  - Outside Conferences - Convocation, Toward the Year 2018: The Challenge to United States Foreign Policy, 1968 May 27-29 (Box 60, Folder 589)
    Foreign Policy Association, New York. Addresses by Barbara Ward, and J. D. B. Miller (Political and Ideological Trends of the Underdeveloped Nations).
- Publications and Reports, 1980-1983; 6; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Notes from the National Committee - Subscription Requests, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Notes from the National Committee - Subscription Requests (Non-Members Mailing List), 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 56)
- Programs, Projects, and Proposals, 1968-2001; 8; 6.39 Cubic Feet
  The Programs, Projects, and Proposals series in RG 9 contains records relating to the National Committee's Field Staff programs, 1968-1976; the Luce Foundation – funded Civil Society Project, 1995-2000; and the Scholar Orientation Program (SOP), from the mid-1980s through the late 1990s.
  The Field Staff files cover the program for the period 1971-1976 and include program and grant correspondence and reports, as well as correspondence with individual university field staff offices. Files on Berkeley and Stanford date from 1968 and concern efforts to establish an office in the Bay area. Early records concerning the other university field staffs (1967-1973) are found in RG 2 (FA1184).
  A three-year grant from the Henry Luce Foundation in 1997 funded a project to explore the development of civil society in China, particularly with regard to the localization of decision-making authority and privatization of the economy. Through education and exchange programs, joint U.S. – China working groups shared knowledge and experiences in working to address problems of environmental protection in Northeast China and the privatization of vocational education in Guizhou province.
  Series 8 also includes Scholar Orientation Program files for SOP trips # 60 – 70, COP # 74, and TEP # 77 (spanning the period 1993-1998), plus various files for the 1980s- 1990s concerning program administration, visit planning, readings, etc. The files in RG 9 complete the fuller run of SOP records found in RG 3 (FA1185).
  Finally, the series includes a card file of potential Speakers and Contacts, providing names, qualifications, and other information on a wide range of China experts.
  - Field Staff Program - General, 1971-1975 (Box 16, Folder 161)
    Field Staff List, 1975; Accounting Memos.
  - Field Staff Development File, 1970-1975 (Box 16, Folder 162)
  - Field Staff Program - NEH Grant Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 16, Folder 163)
    NEH (National Endowment for the Humanities) grant in support of the National Committee's University Field Staff Program and its Audiotape Program.
  - Field Staff Progress Reports (NEH Grant), 1974-1975 (Box 16, Folder 164)
    Program report for the University Field Staffs and Audiotape programs, September 1974 - August 1975, plus reports on 1974-1975 programs from individual Field Staff offices.
  - Field Staff Program Reports, 1971-1974 (Box 16, Folder 165)
  - Field Staff Memos, 1971-1976 (Box 16, Folder 166-167)
  - Field Staff Conference and Reports, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 168)
    Field staff conference, Denver, September 1972.
  - Field Staff Conferences, 1973-1974 (Box 17, Folder 169)
  - Field Staff Coordinator (Arne J. de Keijzer) - Personal File, 1970-1972 (Box 17, Folder 170)
  - Field Staff - Educational Services Role, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 171)
    Includes memos on National Committee efforts in secondary education.
  - Berkeley - National Committee Liaison, 1968-1970 (Box 17, Folder 172)
  - Colorado Field Staff, 1972-1975 (Box 17, Folder 173)
  - Columbia Field Staff, 1972-1975 (Box 17, Folder 174)
  - Columbia Field Staff - China Today Workshop, 1974 March 1 (Box 17, Folder 175)
    Conference for secondary school students and teachers, Teachers College, Columbia.
  - Hawaii Field Staff, 1971-1975 (Box 17, Folder 176-177)
  - Indiana Field Staff, 1973-1976 (Box 17, Folder 178)
  - Michigan Field Staff, 1972-1976; Oversized poster (17.5 x 22.25) separated from folder 181. (Box 18, Folder 179-181)
  - Northern California Field Staff, 1972-1976 (Box 18, Folder 182-183)
  - St. Louis Field Staff, 1972-1976 (Box 18, Folder 184-185)
    Includes draft lesson package on modern China (14 sections), 1975.
  - Seattle Field Staff, 1972-1976 (Box 19, Folder 186-187)
    Includes reports on BAYCEP's teachers' workshop on China, held at Dominican College, June 1974
  - Seton Hall Field Staff, 1970; 1972-1975 (Box 19, Folder 188)
  - Southern California Field Staff, 1972-1975 (Box 19, Folder 189-190)
  - Stanford Field Staff, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Folder 191)
    See also Northern California Field Staff files.
  - Texas Field Staff, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 192-194)
    Includes materials for April 20, 1974, Teachers Conference on Chinese Civilization and Texas Education.
  - Texas Field Staff, 1975-1976 (Box 20, Folder 195-196)
    Includes transcript of "Misunderstanding China," Charles Kuralt broadcast, February 20, 1972, in 1975 folder.
  - Washington, DC, Field Staff, 1972-1976 (Box 20, Folder 197-198)
  - Education Program, 1973-1974 (Box 20, Folder 199)
    Includes Education Committee minutes and program memos.
  - Program Assistant - Robert Goldberg Chronological File, 1974 January - August (Box 20, Folder 200)
  - Program Associates - Peggy Blumenthal Chronological Files, 1975 - 1976 August (Box 20, Folder 201-202)
  - Program Associates - Arne J. de Keijzer Chronological Files, 1975 - 1977 August (Box 21, Folder 203-206)
    Correspondence for 1975 is for January and November only.
  - Program Associates - Arlene Posner Chronological Files, 1975-1976 (Box 21, Folder 207)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - General, 1998-2000 (Box 21, Folder 208)
    Budget, Civil Society readings, correspondence on program and planning.